Guide to The Church of the Redeemer (New Haven, Conn.) Records - Addendum A
Yale University Divinity School Library
Church of the Redeemer (New Haven, Conn.) Records - Addendum A
1840-2009
RG 266A
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(8 boxes)
Reports and publications document the history of The Church of the Redeemer, United Church of Christ (New Haven, Conn.)
Church of the Redeemer (New Haven, Conn.)
Chapel Street Congregational Church (New Haven, Conn.)
Biographical / Historical
Historical statement by Elliott Barske, Church Historian
In 1838 the City of New Haven celebrated its bicentennial year and the fourth Congregational Church in the area came into being when on November 4th the Chapel Street Congregational Church was organized and declared a Church of Christ with 61 members. This congregation was eventually to become the Church of the Redeemer.
Two hundred years before in 1638, the New Haven Colony was settled under the leadership of Reverend John Davenport and Theophilus Eaton who established the First Church, now Center Church on the Green. Gradually over the early years schisms arose and the period of The Great Awakening and the teachings of Jonathan Edwards led to the formation of dissenting groups such as the White Haven Church and the Fair Haven Society. These two groups merged in 1796 to form North Church on the Green, the Second Church of New Haven, now known as United Church.
The Third Congregational Church was formed in 1826 under the leadership of Dr. Nathaniel W. Taylor, a Professor of Theology in Yale College and a former pastor of Center Church. The founding members of the Third included 19 from Center Church and 10 from United Church. This congregation was disrupted after a new pastor, Dr. E. L. Cleaveland, who was installed in 1833, would not accept the "new theology" of Nathaniel Taylor. Many members of Third stood by Dr. Taylor and under his spiritual guidance organized and founded the Chapel Street Congregational Church. At the organization meeting Timothy Dwight, Jr., son of the President of Yale, acted as Chairman and became very active in the government of the new church.
During the over 170 years of our history, there have been 17 Pastors of whom the longest serving were Reverend John E. Todd 1869-1890 and Reverend Watson L. Phillips 1890-1915. Both were serving during the two major relocations of the church. Todd was present when our Second House of Worship at Orange and Wall Streets was dedicated on May 25, 1871 and the name changed to the Church of the Redeemer. Phillips was involved in the move to Cold Spring Street and Whitney Ave where the Parish House was dedicated on October 10, 1920. After 30 years of planning and fund raising the present Main Sanctuary was completed and dedicated on May 20, 1951 during the pastorate of the Reverend Robert E. Luccock.
MINISTRIES PAST TO PRESENT Rev. John O. Colton 1839-1840 Rev. Joseph P. Thompson 1840-1845 Rev. Leverett Griggs 1845-1847 Rev. William T. Eustis 1848-1869 Rev. John E. Todd 1869-1890 Rev. Watson L. Phillips 1890-1915 Rev. Roy M. Houghton 1917-1931 Rev. R. Hawley Fitch 1932-1935 Rev. Phillip G. Scott 1936-1949 Rev. Robert E. Luccock 1950-1962 Rev. Charles L. Ives 1962-1964 Rev. C. Arthur Bradley 1964-1981 Rev. Dr. Thomas Burgett-Leutner 1981-1994 Rev. Olivia Robinson 1994-1996 (interim) Rev. Lillian F. Daniel 1996-2004 Rev. Dr. Duncan Newcomer 2004-2006 (interim) Rev. Dr. Rochelle A. Stackhouse 2006-Present
Scope and Contents
Reports and publications document the history of The Church of the Redeemer, United Church of Christ (New Haven, Conn.)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to qualified researchers.
- Historical Records, 1840-1989; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Early records of the church, likely duplicated at the New Haven Museum.
  - Chapel Street Congregational Church (Chapel St and Union Ave), 1840-1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church of the Redeemer (Orange and Wall Sts.), 1872-1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church of the Redeemer (Orange and Wall Sts.), 1891-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church of the Redeemer (Orange and Wall Sts.), 1895-1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church of the Redeemer (Whitney Ave at Cold Spring St., as of 1920), 1911-1963, 1981, 1989, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Administrative Records, 1966-2000; Series II
  - Annual report, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual report, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual report, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual report, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual report, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual report, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual report, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual report, 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual report, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual report, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annual report, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annual report, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual report, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annual report, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Annual report, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annual report, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Annual report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Annual report, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Church Governing Bodies, 1964-2004; Series III
  Series 3, Church Governing Bodies, includes records of the Church Council, Board of Deacons, Christian Education and various church committees.
  - Church Council
    - Minutes (bound volume), 1964-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Minutes (bound volume), 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1992-1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 2000-2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee of the Church Council
    - Minutes, 1986-1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Board of Deacons
    - Minutes, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1993-1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, 2000-2004 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Christian Education Committee
    - Minutes, 1969-1979 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, 1987-1995 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Mintues, 1996-2003 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Job descriptions of Christian Education staff, 1985, 1989, 1999, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Christian Education Director Search Committee, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Christian Education Staff, 1984, 1999, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Christian Education Handbook, 2004-05 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Long Range Planning Committee
    - Minutes, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Minutes, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Missions Committee
    - Minutes, including Our Christian World Missions/Our Church's Wider Mission, 1974-1981 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Minutes, 1982-2004 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Christian Action Committee
    - Minutes and correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Minutes and correspondence, 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Minutes and correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Clerk Files: Membership and Staff Records, 1962-2006; Series IV
  - Clerk's records (bound volume), 1962-1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clerk's records (bound volume), 1977-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Membership directories, 1963-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Membership directories, 1980-1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Membership directories, 1991-1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Membership directories, 1998-2004 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - The Rev. C. Arthur Bradley: sermons, prayers, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Installation of the Rev. Thomas A. Burgett-Leutner (a.k.a. Thomas A. Leutner), Senior Minister, 1981 Nov 29 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ordination of Sue E. Kasserman, 1984 Dec 2 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Ordination of Tina F. Burgett-Leutner (a.k.a. Tina F. Burgett), 1986 June 15 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Installation of Elizabeth C. Myrick, Associate Minister, 1987 Sep 27 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Service of celebration and recognition of the ministry of The Rev. Ron Kittel, 1989 May 7 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Ordination of Verlee Ann North-Shea, 1989 May 28 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Senior Minister Search Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - The Rev. Lillian F. Daniel, Senior Minister: sermons, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 16-17)
  - Kenneth Minkema: lay sermon, 1997 Feb 16 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Tom Caruso: lay sermon, 1997 Jul 13 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - The Rev. Dr. Richard Wood: sermon, 1997 Oct 26 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Chris Olson, Intern: sermon, 1997 Nov 30 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Ordination of Philip Gerenia, 1998 May 30 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - The Rev. William Oliver III: sermons, 1998 Mar 22, Jul 5 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Thomas Holahan: lay sermon, 1998 Jul 12 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Sam Dexter, Intern: sermons, 1998 Oct-Nov (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Ordination of Samuel Adam Dexter, Associate Minister, 2000 Oct 14 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - The Rev. Dr. Duncan D. Newcomer, Interim Senior Minister: sermons, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Kaji Spellman, Intern: sermon, 2004 Aug 29 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Member testimonies, 2004 Jul-Aug (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Installation of The Rev. Dr. Rochelle A. Stackhouse, Senior Minister, 2006 Oct 1 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Weddings, 1984-2003 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Funerals, 1981-2003 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Farewell to the Warren family, [n.d.] (Box 8, Folder 33)
- Publications, 1982-2009; Series V
  - Bulletins, 1982 Jun-Dec (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1983 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1984 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1985 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins, 1986 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins, 1987 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins, 1988 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 1989 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 1990 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1991 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 1992 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1993 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 1994 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 1995 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, 1996 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins (draft copies), 1997 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins, 1997 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1998 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1998 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1998 Jun-Sep (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1998 Jun-Sep (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1998 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins, 1998 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1999 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 1999 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1999 Apr-Jun (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1999 Apr-Jun (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1999 Jul-Sep (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1999 Oct-Nov (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 1999 Dec (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 1999 Jul-Dec (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 2000 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, 2000 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 2000 Apr-Jun (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Bulletins, 2000 Apr-Jun (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bulletins (incl. drafts final), 2000 Jul-Oct (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bulletins (incl. drafts final), 2000 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 2001 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 2001 Apr-Jun (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 2001 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins (drafts), 2001 Aug-Nov (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins, 2001 Jul-Nov (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins (incl. drafts final), 2001 Dec (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins, 2002 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 2003 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 2004 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 2004 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 2005 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 2005 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 2006 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 2006 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, 2007 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, 2007 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins, 2008 Jan-June (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bulletins, 2008 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bulletins, 2009 Jan-Jun (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bulletins, 2009 Jul-Dec (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)